[
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What does the acronym 'GNU' stand for in GNU/Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "Global Network Utilities",
        "General Network Utility",
        "GNU's Not Unix",
        "Graphical Network Utilities"
      ],
      "correctOption": "GNU's Not Unix",
      "explanation": "GNU stands for 'GNU's Not Unix,' indicating that Linux is inspired by Unix but not a direct derivative."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which command is used to display the current directory in the terminal?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "pwd",
        "ls",
        "cd",
        "dir"
      ],
      "correctOption": "pwd",
      "explanation": "The pwd command stands for 'print working directory' and displays the current directory."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which shell is the default command-line interface in most Linux distributions?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "Bash",
        "Csh",
        "Zsh",
        "Ksh"
      ],
      "correctOption": "Bash",
      "explanation": "Bash (Bourne Again SHell) is the default shell in many Linux distributions."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the ls command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "List installed applications",
        "List files and directories",
        "List system processes",
        "List network connections"
      ],
      "correctOption": "List files and directories",
      "explanation": "The ls command is used to list files and directories in a directory."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which directory is the home directory for the root user in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "/home/root",
        "/root",
        "/home",
        "/user/root"
      ],
      "correctOption": "/root",
      "explanation": "The home directory for the root user is /root."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the command to create a new directory in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "newdir",
        "create dir",
        "mkdir",
        "mkd"
      ],
      "correctOption": "mkdir",
      "explanation": "The mkdir command is used to create a new directory in Linux."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which file is used to store user-specific environment variables in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        ".bashrc",
        ".profile",
        ".env",
        ".config"
      ],
      "correctOption": ".bashrc",
      "explanation": "User-specific environment variables are typically stored in the .bashrc file."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What does the command chmod +x script.sh do in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "Renames the script",
        "Deletes the script",
        "Makes the script executable",
        "Changes the script's permissions to read-only"
      ],
      "correctOption": "Makes the script executable",
      "explanation": "chmod +x script.sh makes the script executable by adding the execute permission."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux command is used to find files and directories based on their names?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "find",
        "locate",
        "search",
        "grep"
      ],
      "correctOption": "find",
      "explanation": "The find command is used to search for files and directories based on their names."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the default package manager for Debian-based Linux distributions like Ubuntu?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "yum",
        "apt",
        "pacman",
        "dnf"
      ],
      "correctOption": "apt",
      "explanation": "The default package manager for Debian-based distributions is apt (Advanced Package Tool)."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux distribution is known for its use in servers and supercomputers due to its stability and long-term support (LTS) releases?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "Ubuntu",
        "Fedora",
        "CentOS",
        "Arch Linux"
      ],
      "correctOption": "CentOS",
      "explanation": "CentOS is known for its stability and is commonly used in server environments."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the grep command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "It displays the calendar",
        "It searches for text patterns in files",
        "It creates new files",
        "It compresses files"
      ],
      "correctOption": "It searches for text patterns in files",
      "explanation": "The grep command is used to search for text patterns in files."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "In Linux, what is the purpose of the /etc/passwd file?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "It stores user passwords",
        "It contains system logs",
        "It lists user accounts and their information",
        "It stores system configuration settings"
      ],
      "correctOption": "It lists user accounts and their information",
      "explanation": "The /etc/passwd file lists user accounts and their information."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which command is used to display the manual pages (documentation) for Linux commands?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "help",
        "man",
        "info",
        "docs"
      ],
      "correctOption": "man",
      "explanation": "The man command is used to display the manual pages for Linux commands."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What does the acronym 'CLI' stand for in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "Command Line Interface",
        "Common Language Interface",
        "Command Line Instruction",
        "Command Line Input"
      ],
      "correctOption": "Command Line Interface",
      "explanation": "CLI stands for 'Command Line Interface.'"
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux command is used to compress files and directories into a single archive file?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "zip",
        "tar",
        "gzip",
        "compress"
      ],
      "correctOption": "tar",
      "explanation": "The tar command is used to create archives, and you can use additional commands like gzip for compression."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the cron service in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To manage user accounts",
        "To schedule and automate tasks",
        "To monitor system resources",
        "To control network services"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To schedule and automate tasks",
      "explanation": "The cron service is used to schedule and automate tasks in Linux."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux file system is known for its use in flash drives and SSDs due to its wear-leveling capabilities?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "NTFS",
        "ext4",
        "FAT32",
        "btrfs"
      ],
      "correctOption": "btrfs",
      "explanation": "btrfs is a Linux file system known for its use in flash drives and SSDs."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What does the command ps aux display in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "A list of installed packages",
        "A list of running processes for all users",
        "A list of available network interfaces",
        "A list of user accounts"
      ],
      "correctOption": "A list of running processes for all users",
      "explanation": "ps aux displays a list of running processes for all users."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux command is used to change the ownership of files and directories?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "own",
        "chown",
        "chmod",
        "usermod"
      ],
      "correctOption": "chown",
      "explanation": "The chown command is used to change the ownership of files and directories."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the sudo command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To create a new user",
        "To switch to the root user",
        "To run commands with superuser privileges",
        "To list installed software"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To run commands with superuser privileges",
      "explanation": "The sudo command is used to run commands with superuser privileges."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "In Linux, what is the purpose of the /etc/fstab file?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "It stores user passwords",
        "It lists user accounts",
        "It contains information about disk partitions and mount points",
        "It stores system logs"
      ],
      "correctOption": "It contains information about disk partitions and mount points",
      "explanation": "The /etc/fstab file contains information about disk partitions and their mount points."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux distribution is community-driven and follows the rolling release model, where updates are continuously released rather than having version numbers?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "Fedora",
        "Debian",
        "Arch Linux",
        "openSUSE"
      ],
      "correctOption": "Arch Linux",
      "explanation": "Arch Linux follows the rolling release model."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What does the command df -h display in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "A list of available software repositories",
        "Disk usage statistics for mounted file systems in a human-readable format",
        "A list of currently logged-in users",
        "Directory permissions"
      ],
      "correctOption": "Disk usage statistics for mounted file systems in a human-readable format",
      "explanation": "df -h displays disk usage statistics for mounted file systems in a human-readable format."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "In Linux, what is the purpose of the /etc/apt/sources.list file?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To store user passwords",
        "To list available hardware devices",
        "To configure software repositories for package management",
        "To define environment variables"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To configure software repositories for package management",
      "explanation": "The /etc/apt/sources.list file is used to configure software repositories for package management."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the iptables command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To display system information",
        "To configure network firewall rules",
        "To create user accounts",
        "To manage software packages"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To configure network firewall rules",
      "explanation": "The iptables command is used to configure network firewall rules in Linux."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux directory contains system startup scripts that are executed during boot?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "/etc/startup",
        "/init.d",
        "/startup",
        "/etc/init.d"
      ],
      "correctOption": "/etc/init.d",
      "explanation": "The /etc/init.d directory contains system startup scripts."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the dd command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To delete files and directories",
        "To display disk space usage",
        "To create disk images and copy data block by block",
        "To compress files"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To create disk images and copy data block by block",
      "explanation": "The dd command is used to create disk images and copy data block by block."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux file contains information about the system's network configuration and hostname?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "/etc/network.conf",
        "/etc/hostname",
        "/etc/resolv.conf",
        "/etc/network/interfaces"
      ],
      "correctOption": "/etc/hostname",
      "explanation": "The /etc/hostname file contains the system's hostname."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the rsync command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To rename files",
        "To synchronize files and directories between different locations",
        "To compress files",
        "To synchronize files in installed packages"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To synchronize files and directories between different locations",
      "explanation": "The rsync command is used to synchronize files and directories between different locations."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux command is used to view the contents of a compressed file without extracting it?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "cat",
        "unzip",
        "tar",
        "zcat"
      ],
      "correctOption": "zcat",
      "explanation": "The zcat command is used to view the contents of a compressed file."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the primary purpose of the chroot command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To change the root directory for a process",
        "To switch to a different shell",
        "To create a new user account",
        "To display system logs"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To change the root directory for a process",
      "explanation": "The chroot command is used to change the root directory for a process."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "In Linux, what does the command whoami display?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "The current date and time",
        "The list of currently logged-in users",
        "The username of the current user",
        "The system's hostname"
      ],
      "correctOption": "The username of the current user",
      "explanation": "The whoami command displays the username of the current user."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux utility is used to monitor and manage system performance in real-time?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "top",
        "free",
        "uptime",
        "ps"
      ],
      "correctOption": "top",
      "explanation": "The top command is used to monitor and manage system performance in real-time."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the mmap system call in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To create memory-mapped files",
        "To change file permissions",
        "To mount external storage devices",
        "To display file metadata"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To create memory-mapped files",
      "explanation": "The mmap system call is used to create memory-mapped files in Linux."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the primary role of the Linux kernel in the operating system?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To provide a graphical user interface (GUI)",
        "To manage hardware resources and provide core functionality",
        "To run user applications",
        "To provide a web browser"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To manage hardware resources and provide core functionality",
      "explanation": "The primary role of the Linux kernel is to manage hardware resources and provide core functionality."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What does the acronym 'LVM' stand for in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "Linux Virtual Machine",
        "Logical Volume Manager",
        "Large Virtual Memory",
        "Linux Volume Mapping"
      ],
      "correctOption": "Logical Volume Manager",
      "explanation": "LVM stands for 'Logical Volume Manager,' which allows for flexible disk storage management."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "What is the purpose of the kill command in Linux?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To create new processes",
        "To terminate running processes",
        "To display process information",
        "To schedule tasks"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To terminate running processes",
      "explanation": "The kill command is used to terminate running processes in Linux."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "Which Linux utility is used to analyze and troubleshoot network-related issues, including packet capture?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "ifconfig",
        "netstat",
        "tcpdump",
        "traceroute"
      ],
      "correctOption": "tcpdump",
      "explanation": "tcpdump is used to capture and analyze network packets."
    },
    {
      "quizTitle":"Linux",
      "quizQuestion": "In Linux, what is the purpose of the /var/log directory?",
      "quizOptions": [
        "To store user home directories",
        "To store temporary files",
        "To store system log files",
        "To store configuration files"
      ],
      "correctOption": "To store system log files",
      "explanation": "The /var/log directory is used to store system log files."
    }
  ]
  